Finding Aid for the Akahori Family papers, ca. 1908-1965 LSC.2010.01
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Wartime internment
  - Santa Fe
    - Sadaichi Furugochi, "Kanpu eiseiho: dai ippen" [characters] [Hygeine in the camp, part 1], Santa Fe, 1943 (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - Letters drafted on behalf on the Santa Fe Camp spokesperson, 1943 June-October (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - Memos regarding Akahori's internment at Santa Fe, 1943-1944 (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - "Shinnen tanzaku tenrankai" [characters] [New Year exhibition of tanzaku], 1944 January 3 (Box 34, Folder 10)
      A collection of tanka, haiku, and senri poems composed by Santa Fe Camp internees.
    - Religious publications at Santa Fe, 1944 (Box 34, Folder 11)
      3 leaflets and notices
  - Crystal City
    - Notes and ephemera relating to the internment life of the Akahoris at Crystal City, ca.1944-1945 (Box 34, Folder 12)
    - "Hibi no chikara" [characters] [Daily strength], no.1-12, Crystal City, [1946], 1954-1955 (Box 34, Folder 13)
      Diary entries written on the sides of pages.
    - Documents regarding the Jichikai [characters] [the organization for self-government] of the Crystal City Internment Camp, 1944 January-1945 June (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Akahori's handwritten memos taken at various Jichikai meetings in Crystal City, ca.1944 April-July (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - "Nihonjin Kazoku meibo" [characters] [Japanese family roster], Crystal City, ca.1945-1946 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - "Kikokusha kachomei narabini kazokuso (ABC jun)" [characters] [Rostor of repatriators: an alphabetical listing of the names of household heads with the numbers of family members], Crystal City, 1945 November 29 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Jichikai kaijo [characters] [Jichikai circulars], Crystal City, 1944 April 5-October 20 (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Scattered issues of the "Jichikai Jiho" [characters] [Jichikai Times], no.42-434, Crystal City, 1944 January 18-1946 March 14 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Masaru's notes from a series of lectures given by Dr. Motoichi Mori on world politics and other related topics, Crystal City, 1944 (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Akahori's handwritten memos taken at Suishoshi Dokushokai [characters] [Crystal City Reading Club] lecture series, 1944 (Box 35, Folder 8)
      Mostly on lectures given by Dr. Mori. In Japanese.
    - Akahori's lecture notes from the camp at Crystal City, ca.1944-1945 (Box 35, Folder 9)
    - Two copies of letters written by Japanese spokespersons for the internees at Crystal City., 1945 March and December (Box 35, Folder 10)
    - Official War Relocation Authority (WRA) announcement at Crystal City, ca.1945 (Box 35, Folder 11)
    - Programs of athletic and educational events held at the Crystal City Internment Camp, 1944 April-December (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Notices of the Kurisutaru Shichi kirisuto kyokai [characters] [Crystal City Japanese Christian Church], 1944 March-1945 March (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Kanshi [characters] [Chinese poems] and other verses composed by Akahori and other internees at Crystal City upon hearing the news about the end of the war and thereafter., August 1945 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - Notes and letters regarding off-camp site hiking trips of the internees at Crystal City organized by Akahori., 1946 February-March (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Documents regarding the repatriation of Peruvian Japanese interned at Crystal City., 1946 February-April (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Akahori's scrapbook entitled "Tessaku sekatsu gonen" [characters] [Five years behind barbed wires], 1941-1946 (Box 36, Folder 6)
      Contains photographs and mementos of the internment camps.
    - Notes and ephemera relating to postwar get-togethers of former internees in Los Angeles, 1952 and 1954 (Box 36, Folder 7)
- Postwar business records
  - Documents relating to an employment agency Akahori started in Little Tokyo, Los Angeles, 1946 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    This was the first business that Akahori started after his release from the internment camp. On July 1, 1946, however, he transferred the title to the employment agency to Kamekichi Sasaki, fellow internee at Crystal City, so that he could start publishing the Town Crier.
  - Correspondence and other papers relating to Phil Boland Enterprises, 1946 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    Regarding a proposal for opening a bank in Little Tokyo, Los Angeles; a reception for the visit of Prince Kuni; and a plan to establish a non-profit organization to aid illegitimate children of American GI's born in Japan.
  - Akahori's postwar office records regarding the divorce of Yahei Naruto, Los Angeles, 1946 May-December (Box 36, Folder 10)
    Mostly correspondence exchanged between Naruto and his children.
  - Akahori's postwar office records regarding the naturalization of an Issei who returned to the U.S. after a prolonged stay in Japan, 1952-1959 (Box 36, Folder 11)
  - Akahori's postwar office records regarding the Rafu Nihonjin Shogyokumiai [characters] [Association of Japanese shop-owners in Los Angeles] and Kashujinkai [characters] [Association of former Washington State residents in Los Angeles], undated (Box 36, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and other postwar office records regarding Okinawa ryokka undo [characters] [Movement to plant trees in Okinawa], 1959 (Box 36, Folder 13)
  - Court documents on litigations involving Akahori, Los Angeles Municipal Court., 1947 March-December (Box 36, Folder 14)
- Financial records
  - Receipts and invoices, ca.1923-1941 (Box 36, Folder 15)
  - Account books and bank statements, ca.1950-1960 (Box 37)
    Includes eight account books on Akahori's personal and business expenses and a folder containing bank statements and cancelled checks.
- Published materials collected by Masaru Akahori
  - Issues of various theatrical magazines published in Japan, ca.1926 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - A collection of printed programs for the performances of Satsuma and Chikuzen biwa [characters] [Japanese lute] at Nihonkan [characters] [Japanese Hall], in Seattle, 1923-1935 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Clippings from various Japanese language newspapers printed in Los Angeles, 1931-1932 (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Pamphlets from the Sangyo Nippo and related materials, ca.1939-1941 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - "Miscellaneous Clippings", 1934 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    A collection of clippings from various newspaper and magazine articles.
  - "America in Danger!" Bulletin no. 113-118., 1938 April 3-May 9 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    Bulletins printed and circulated by Chas. B. Budson of Omaha, Nebraska. Its objective was a weekly exposé of un-American-ism in education, finance, labor, politics, and religion for truth-seeking readers.
  - "Gakusei no mita amerika" [characters] [America, as seen by visiting Japanese students], 1935 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    A collection of essays written by those visiting Japanese students.
  - Reports and references on Freemasons, 1927 and ca.1931 (Box 39, Folder 3)
    Includes the Constitution of Mystic Knights of the Flaming Cross.
  - Materials relating to the establishment of the North American Daijingu, a Shinto shrine, in Terminal Island., 1932 June (Box 39, Folder 4)
    Includes a sketch, power of attorney, notes, and blue prints.
  - Correspondence relating to the Japan Aid Society of America, a Japanese organization in Los Angeles., 1935 October 1, 1940-1941 (Box 39, Folder 5)
    In Japanese.
  - Statistical data on the number of Japanese living in the U.S., 1931 (Box 39, Folder 6)
    Includes data provided by the Japanese Consulates in San Francisco and Los Angeles, the California Department of Health and a newspaper clipping.
  - Postwar news clippings
    - Newspaper clippings on the end of World War II, 1945 August (Box 39, Folder 7)
      Includes clippings from the "Los Angeles Examiner," "New York Times," and "Yuta Nippo" [characters] [Utah Daily News].
    - Clippings from the "Nichibei Jiji" [characters] [Japan America Times] of San Francisco, 1946 (Box 39, Folder 8)
      Mostly clippings of "Nanka dayori" [characters] [correspondence from Southern California] written by Hyoroku Oishi (Masaru Akahori) for the newspaper.
    - A scrapbook of clippings from various Japanese language newspapers, 1948 January-October (Box 39, Folder 9)
    - "Shinnengo furoku" [characters] [New Year supplement], no. 1-4 of the "Nichibei Jiji", 1955 January 1 (Box 39, Folder 10)
    - Undated (postwar?) newspaper clippings (Box 39, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings given as a gift to Akahori from a friend, 1934 (Box 241, Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook of English language newspaper clippings, 1938 August-December (Box 241, Folder 2)
    Mostly from the "Post-Intelligencer," Seattle, Washington.
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings of articles Akahori wrote as a Sacremento-based reporter for the "Nichibei," a Japanese language daily in San Francisco, 1908-1911 (Box 241, Folder 3)